Inventory of the A. Verbouwe collection
Hoover Institution Archives
A. Verbouwe collection
1914-1918
XX437
Verbouwe, A., collector.
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box (1.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection contains underground serial materials issued in German-occupied Belgium, summaries of World War I news, and other printed matter.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains underground serial materials issued in German occupied Belgium, summaries of World War I news, and other printed matter. Although some serials were printed, many were mimeographed or written by hand. The editors' sources of information were often concealed wireless receivers, items dropped from airplanes, and information smuggled across the frontier. Publishers often gave the address, "Ghent under the open sky" to denote underground materials. Many of the papers were intended to not only supply news to the inhabitants, but also to encourage resistance and harass the German occupiers.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; Belgium--History--German occupation, 1914-1918.
Collection Contents
- Serials, 1914-1918 (Box 1)
  - News extracts, 1914-1915 (Folder 1: 1-9)
  - L'Assiette au Beurre, 1915 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Auszug aus der Tagespresse, Belgien, 1916-1918 (Folder 1: 10)
  - L'Assiette au Beurre, 1915 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Bulletin, 1914-1915 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Le Clou, circa 1915 (Folder 1: 13)
  - La Currée, 1915 (Folder 1: 13)
  - L'Écho, de ce que les Journaux censurés n'osent ou ne peuvent pas dire, 1916 (Folder 1: 14)
  - L'écho Libre, 1916 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Informations, 1914-1915 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Les Jeunes, circa 1914 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Jour De Guerre, 1916 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Journal de von Bissing, 1915 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Méli-Mélo, 1916 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Les Nouvelles de la Guerre, 1915-1916 (Folder 1: 20-22)
  - De Paaschklok, circa 1914 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Réponse à la lettre ouverte d'un Philanthrope par un Patriote Belge, 1915 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Satirische Zeitung, 1916 (Folder 1: 25-27)
  - Sint Antonius Klok, 1916-1917 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Six Mois de Guerre en Belgique par un soldat Belge, 1914-1915 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Le Sourire d'Andromaque, 1917 (Folder 1: 30)
  - La Vérité, 1914 (Folder 1: 31-34)
- Oversize serials, 1914-1919 (Folder 2)
  - L'Assiette au Beurre, 1915 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Ce que vaut le "Livre Blanc,", 1915 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Le Cultivateur, Brussels, 1915-1918 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Dernieres Nouvelles, 1914-1915 (Folder 2: 4-5)
  - Het Nachtlightje, 1915 (Folder 2: 6)
  - De Landbouwer, Brussels, 1915-1918 (Folder 2: 7-9)
  - Liste Officielle des Soldats Prisonniers, 1914 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Ons Fulhamsch Volk, 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 11-12)
  - Wolf's Telegraphisches Bureau, 1914-1918 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Maps, brochures, and postcards, 1914-1919 (Folder 2: 14-15)